Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
I can cut a thousand strands of hair;
But I cannot sever the tangled threads on my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
What a clever woman.
Do you know...
what I would do...
to a clever woman?
You'd kill me?
Unfortunately, the Dzungars would never
kill someone who saves them.
I have no intention of killing you.
A clever woman
who is beautiful at the same time...
can easily be an object of desire.
Sir,
your remarks are out of line.
We Dzungars...
are not shy about what we like.
When we fancy a thing,
we do everything we can to acquire it.
Don't forget...
This is the land of the Great Qing.
The day may come
when this land becomes the territory of the Dzungars.
We saved your life just now.
But we can kill you just as easily.
Can you?
It wouldn't be so easy.
In the past, at least your country had Nian Gengyao.
But now,
you don't have a single competent general.
You're less capable than a runaway soldier.
I don't think you're worthy of my concern.
You're lucky
because I will not harm an injured man.
Sir!
Sir! Sir!
It was so hard to find you.
What happened?
I was...
bitten by a poisonous snake up the hill.
Luckily they saved me.
Thank you very much, sir,
and the two ladies,
for saving My Lord.
You should be more careful going out in the future.
The next time,
you might not be so lucky to leave unscathed.
That's very caring of you.
It may seem so,
but only because you value your own life.
To use a phrase from your language ...
you could be considered almost a soul mate of mine.
You said that as a compliment,
but it will be my life-long fortune
to never again see your lordly face.
Please suit yourself.
Here, master.
Let's go, master.
Be careful.
Good.
Thank you.
Take it slow.
Let's go.
Why did you bring so many books?
Where are they from?
I boldly asked His Lordship for some books.
He sent Ajin to deliver these today.
It is enough for me to read
my few books for leisure.
Why did you ask him for so many?
My Lady, can you teach me literary classics?
But you've never been interested in poetry and prose.
What changed your mind?
Isn't it good for me to know more about literature?
My Lady, you've always had a passion for reading.
If I can understand literature better,
I can help relieve your boredom.
My Lady, you have His Lordship now,
and you two are like a couple in a fairy tale.
But can't I keep you company as well?
Don't sidestep the real issue.
Let me ask you,
when I was composing poetry with him a few days ago,
you heard us, didn't you?
Since you have figured me out,
I won't hide it anymore.
My Lady, you and His Lordship are so knowledgeable
and fluently hold intelligent conversations all day.
Yet I don't understand anything.
The other day...
when I heard how beautifully
you two composed poetry together,
I stood as dumb as a piece of wood.
I couldn't be more ashamed.
Wishing to improve oneself is a most desirable trait.
As long as you're willing to learn,
I'm always happy to teach you.
It's just that...
the more a woman reads and learns,
the more melancholy and wistful she may feel.
But that's still better
than being ignorant and senseless.
Please request My Lady to come out
to receive His Majesty's decree.
Mr. Su,
you don't know My Lady's personality.
She's intractable like an untamed horse.
She's training a horse right now.
She will definitely not come out.
If you wait for her here,
it could be four to six hours.
Can your task be delayed so long?
My goodness!
She can afford to wait, but I can't.
I need to get back to attend to His Majesty.
Mr. Su,
I know you're afraid of horses...
But don't worry —
even though the horse is wild by nature,
it definitely won't hurt you
while My Lady is present.
Your Majesty, why have you taken a liking to this one?
My Lady, you've finally come
to receive His Majesty's decree.
Say what you have to.
By His Majesty's decree...
I apologize, My Lady,
but you must kneel to receive the decree.
By the Grace of Heaven, His Majesty decrees:
“Ye from the Summer Palace has
a keen intellect and an elegant manner."
"She is awarded the title of Companion
and will be relocated to the palace."
This is His Majesty's edict.
My Lady,
you need to thank His Majesty.
Thanks.
Congratulations, Lady Ye.
How fortunate you are!
Palace servants usually start from the rank of Escort.
But you've leapt to the rank of Companion.
Do you want this kind of fortune?
My Lady, you must be joking!
Must be joking!
Please pack up and get ready for the move.
Where will I live in the palace?
The Household Department will take care of it.
The Household Department has their own work to do.
Since His Majesty likes me,
why would he let the Household Department
arrange this for me?
I don't like noise.
Please tell His Majesty
to settle me in a remote and quiet place.
Yes,
His Majesty will certainly arrange that for you.
My Lady, please hurry.
You still need to thank His Majesty in person.
I won't be able to wait until he comes.
I promised him a performance.
My Lady, who are you talking about?
None of your business.
Look at this fish.
Its eyes are bulging out.
This one looks pretty.
Peace to Your Majesty the Empress Dowager.
Peace to Your Majesty the Empress.
Peace to Your Highness Concubine Astuce.
Rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
I appreciate you taking time from your busy schedule.
It's my pleasure.
Although arrangements have been made discreetly,
she will be living in a palace sooner or later.
How long did the Emperor think he could hide it from me?
Let me ask you,
has the new concubine entered the palace?
What new concubine?
Why don't I know about it?
Because of your high virtue and gentle temperament,
the emperor believes that you would never oppose him.
So he has no scruples about bringing
any woman into the palace.
Please don't be angry, Your Majesty.
She might be coming from a humble background.
Just like Lady Melodic, who was a palace servant.
At worst,
she could be a slave like the mother of Lord VIII.
Even a member of the slave caste
was born to slaves who served officials.
The Emperor chose a multitalented woman this time -
a horse trainer from the stables in the Summer Palace.
Your Majesty,
she has already entered the palace.
His Majesty was concerned about her day and night
while she was still in the Summer Palace.
So His Majesty granted her the rank of Companion
and moved her to the palace.
Has it been decided where to place her?
Not yet.
But Companion Ye has told me that
she prefers a quiet and secluded place.
Listen to this.
She is making demands even before
moving into the palace!
Exactly.
Has the emperor made a decision on her residence?
The Household Department needs several days
to clean and prepare the rooms.
His Majesty said she could live in the side chamber
of the Hall of Mental Cultivation for now.
That can't happen!
You tell the emperor that
the Hall of Spring Joy behind the
Palace of Longevity is unoccupied.
Have it cleaned for her immediately.
Yes.
The Hall of Spring Joy?
How could she deserve such an honor？
Of course she does.
Based on the current situation,
I'm afraid that she will receive
more promotions in the future.
Since she likes peace and quiet,
there's no quieter area than the Palace of Longevity.
I'll have her live under my nose
in case she plays any tricks.
There is no need.
Sit down.
What's wrong?
Are you upset?
Are you still not used to living here？
I'm like this wherever I live.
You've been here for days,
but I haven't seen you smile once.
If you feel constrained by life in the palace,
I'll take you to the Summer Palace
for a visit when I have time.
Your Majesty is busy with state affairs.
There is no need to worry about me.
Besides, I don't smile...
because it is not in my nature.
There is no other reason.
You look even more beautiful when you're not smiling.
Your Majesty,
His Majesty really promoted
a low-born girl to Companion?
Your Majesty,
according to the ancestors' rules,
a maid in the palace should be promoted to Escort first.
Ye Lanyi was not a maid.
Besides, His Majesty likes her.
There is nothing wrong with it.
The promotion ceremony was before noon,
she then accompanied His Majesty for dinner,
and served His Majesty that very night.
In the past few nights, His Majesty
has requested service only from her.
I have never seen His Majesty acting this way.
You haven't? Neither have I.
This is what's called "possessed by the devil".
Today, when I went to the Hall of
Mental Cultivation to pay my respects,
I had a good look at Companion Ye.
Her attitude was arrogant and her manners rough.
I can't fathom what His Majesty likes about her.
Délice, if you are capable,
you can adopt her manners.
Then His Majesty would favor you just the same.
Ye has gained so much favor ...
It makes my heart quiver.
If she gives birth to a low-born scum someday ...
I can't imagine.
It would be a blessing from Heaven if she is barren.
Companion Ye.
Lord XVII.
You're here.
It's been a long time since we last met.
You've become a Companion now.
No one ever asked if I was willing
to be sent to the Palace,
or to become a Companion.
I heard about what happened to you.
You seem dispirited.
Everything here is filthy.
No place feels as pure as the stables at the Hundred Stallion Pavillion.
Do you remember that year
when you almost died from a high fever?
I remember.
It was seven years ago.
I was so sick and about to die.
Nobody cared about a humble servant like me.
But, by chance, Your Lordship saw me
and asked an imperial doctor to save me.
I didn't save you back then
to see you abandoning yourself to despair now.
But what else can I do?
I can't be where I want to be.
The place I'm forced to live -
it disgusts me and destroys my hopes.
You have to protect yourself first.
The Ye Lanyi I remember
has a resilient personality with a radiant smile.
No matter how bitter her life was,
she could find sweetness within it and cheer herself up.
I haven't been able to repay Your Lordship
for your kindness years ago.
Since Your Lordship encourages me to cherish life,
I surely will listen to you.
Excellent.
Huan’er.
Why did you come so suddenly?
As soon as I finished my duties outside,
I hurried here to see you.
A couple days ago,
I said I was feeling troubled, remember?
I came up with an idea that could
put both of us at ease.
Marital horoscope?
Yes,
marital horoscope.
[Traditionally, couples use birth information to confirm
astrological compatibility for marriage.]
I was abandoned by your brother
and my family was disgraced.
My future is still uncertain.
You don’t need to do this.
"We make this life-long vow,
an eternal bond of harmony."
Huan'er,
in this world,
you're the only one I want.
Zhen ...
Huan.
"May the zither accompany the flute;
May peace accompany all our years."
Huan'er,
I will make sure your wish comes true.
I know.
This is merely my wishful thinking.
It will never come to be.
Believe me.
When you fade from His Majesty’s memory,
I’ll ask Madam Abbess to report that you died of illness.
We’ll change our names,
go to a faraway place,
and stay together forever.
Huan'er,
what are you doing?
[Traditionally, couples tie their hair together
as a symbol of sacred union.]
As husband and wife,
we will tie ourselves in one heart for eternity.
Our hearts are eternally united,
one will never forsake the other.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Your Majesty seldomly allows me
to get involved with state affairs.
Ngabo Dorje Gyalpo mounted a rebellion in Tibet.
He intends to ally with the Dzungars.
Although Polhané has mobilized troops
to suppress the rebellion,
I believe
that not until the Dzungar tribes are quelled
will Tibet be stable.
Tibetans won't come to terms,
and the Mongolian tribes harbor treachery.
These two regions...
are a lurking concern for our country.
I appointed imperial residents to govern Tibet,
and I'm planning to...
deploy troops against the Dzungars.
Even so, many things are still unclear.
I need you to go to Yunnan and Tibet
to gather more information.
I'm honored to be trusted by Your Majesty,
but I’m not qualified for the task.
I assigned this to you
because you’re less entangled in the court.
If you go there in plain clothes,
it's easier to probe around
as few people can recognize you.
These days, in Yunnan and Tibet,
there are many Dzungar spies.
I don't want to "beat the grass and startle the snakes".
There is another reason.
If by any chance,
we use military force against the Dzungars,
moving troops from Gansu and Yunnan
would be the fastest.
Consort Dowager Serein is from Yunnan.
You're the most appropriate person to visit the region.
I may have little talent,
but since Your Majesty has entrusted me
with this responsibility, I must abide.
I will do my best.
Good.
Then go prepare for the trip.
The sooner you leave, the sooner you can return.
I shall take my leave.
Su Peisheng.
Your Majesty.
Summon Mr. Zhang Tingyu here.
Yes.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Please rise.
I summoned you here
to discuss Noble Prince Guo's trip
to Yunnan and Tibet.
You need to send reliable people
to protect him carefully and covertly.
Also,
to prevent Noble Prince Guo from
unduly interfering with state affairs.
Wherever he goes,
whoever he talks to,
whatever he does,
must be carefully observed
and reported back in a timely manner.
Yes.
Dr. Wen.
Is the formula ready?
Yes, it is.
Be careful when using it.
Thank you.
Don't thank me.
I just don't want Huan'er
to suffer in an abyss of misery.
I still want to thank you.
Why were you so careless
when dismounting the horse?
Now there is a hole in your cloak.
I haven't seen you for four days,
so I rushed off the horse.
It's only a cloak,
nothing precious.
The mountain roads are difficult on snowy days,
and horses can easily slip.
You didn't have to come here so hurriedly.
It's your cloak this time.
But the next time, you could hurt yourself.
Are you deliberately trying to worry me?
I promise to be careful next time.
I don't want to injure myself either.
If I was injured,
how could I come to see you?
Such a glib tongue.
If your clothes are torn again,
there won't be anyone to mend them for you.
I don't care if you walk around in tattered clothes.
Are you leaving tomorrow?
It's already the 23rd of the last lunar month.
I can't delay any longer.
No matter what, I can't be in Beijing for New Year.
You will be back in forty days?
Within forty days,
I will definitely be back.
Forty days...
The moon will be full once again.
The days will fly by.
I have everything arranged.
After I come back,
I will take you away from here.
Really?
This is...?
Look.
It looks like makeup powder.
Dr. Wen prepared this medicine
for you to feign death.
It's called the Seven-Day Sedate.
Made from jimsonweed.
After taking it,
your breathing will pause
as if you were dead.
Seven days later,
you will regain consciousness.
He is willing to help me after all.
Dr. Wen ...
has put so much thought into helping us.
We must thank him profusely.
I have arranged everything for our plan.
After my obligations are fulfilled,
Huan'er,
at that time,
we will be together forever.
When you come back
and everything is complete,
I will truly be able to put my mind at ease.
Huan'er,
this is of particular concern to the state.
I have to go.
It's only forty days.
I will be here waiting for you.
Back in the day,
an aunt from the south told me that
there is a bridge by West Lake in Hangzhou.
It is called the Long Bridge.
The Long Bridge?
Is the bridge very long?
Actually, it is not long.
It's called the Long Bridge
because the local people say that
Liang Shanbo and Zhu Yingtai
made their farewells on the bridge.
Because they were reluctant to part,
the short bridge felt very long to cross over.
The grief and sorrow of parting
has been the same
from ancient times to now.
I don't want to be like them.
Zhu's father betrothed her to another,
The news caused Liang to vomit blood and die.
Their spirits turned into butterflies
to fly away from this world.
We are much luckier than them.
It was a mistake ...
to compare us to them.
I'm irrationally anxious these days,
and can't bear to hear ill-fated stories.
It is evident that once a man
holds his love dear to his heart,
he can no longer be carefree.
Go and be as carefree as you wish.
Noble Prince Guo has always been
talented and unrestrained.
There is no need to worry about
a lack of beautiful women
delivering themselves to you.
What's the matter with you?
I was only joking,
yet you get so mean to me.
You must be mad because I was right.
You deserved it for talking nonsense.
Even though the flowers will beckon you on the road,
please come back as speedily as possible.
Because...
I will be waiting for you here.
With you here,
my heart will want to return like a shooting arrow.
Huan'er.
I will come back soon.
I will be waiting for you.
Please do.
I will be waiting for you!
I will wait for you.
My Lady,
I have sent the winter coats to Anqi Temple
as you asked.
Her Venerable Highness sent her regards.
She also said that
His Lordship will come back soon
and you should visit her together upon his return.
I've been feeling fatigued recently
and don't want to walk around.
But Yunli will be back within ten days at most.
I will wait for him, and visit
Her Venerable Highness together.
Prioress Mochou,
a distinguished guest from the palace is here.
Meizhuang!
Huan'er!
It's my fault
for not visiting you until today.
Let's sit down.
Finally, we manage to
meet this once after so many years.
Let's cry no more!
For no good reason,
how could you place my sister
in such a remote residence?
I came from Temple of Pure Dew
and it took an hour even on the sedan.
Is this how the temple takes care of concubines
who practice Buddhism outside the palace?
I was sick a while back,
so I moved here to recuperate.
It has nothing to do with Madam Abbess.
Mochou, it's very kind of you to say so.
Yes, yes.
Mochou moved here because she was sick.
All of you, wait outside.
I wish to speak with Mochou privately.
Yes, Your Highness.
Everyone can go,
but Prioress Jingbai is fit and strong.
I ask her to clear the snow off the road
to ease my return to the palace.
To show your respect for Her Highness Concubine Vertu,
please finish it on your own, Prioress.
Yes.
Why did you ask her to do that?
You have endured so much in the Temple of Pure Dew.
Not really.
You still try to hide it from me.
You think I don't know?
You were sent here after being banished
from the palace.
Everyone in this world treads on those
who are lower in status.
Even people in a Buddhist temple
can have worldly dispositions.
When I asked to visit you just now,
Jingbai tried hard to refuse me,
saying the weather was cold and the road slippery.
We barely exchanged words and
she was already showing her guilty conscience.
It's obvious that she bullies you frequently.
I punished her in your presence,
not only to teach her a lesson,
but also to show her you weren't the one
responsible for her punishment,
so she won't retaliate against you later.
It's very thoughtful of you.
It's all right, all right.
I was worried that you suffered greatly.
When Madam Abbess told me that you were
terribly sick and moved away.
I was so scared all the way here.
Seeing you in good health,
I feel some relief now.
I heard you were promoted
to the rank of Concubine.
I was happy for so many days.
What's the use of that?
I don't care about rank or titles.
Why would you think like that?
For the past two years,
His Majesty has been very hard on himself.
He buried himself in work.
Since you left,
His Majesty has been cold towards the harem.
In addition to Concubine Délice,
His Majesty has newly favored
Concubine Fidèle and Attendant Kang.
But it is hard to tell
who he truly adores in the harem.
It didn't become better until
Companion Ye entered the palace several days ago.
Nowadays, His Majesty treats me
with simple courtesy.
It's for the best.
With the rank of Concubine,
I can take more liberty with certain things.
Madam Orchid can often visit me -
because you spoke on my behalf with
the Empress Dowager.
You have done so much for me...
If I were the one suffering,
you would have done the same for me.
Huan'er,
I took your advice
and "blunted my sharp thorn" in the harem
to avoid attracting the Empress’s attention.
I devoted myself to serving the Empress Dowager
and taking care of Longyue with Consort Estime.
So one day ...
I can help redress all the injustices
done to you, in a single blow.
However, after so many years,
I still haven’t gathered much useful evidence.
It’s hard to get out of the palace,
especially in the first lunar month.
How did you manage to come out?
Princess Wenyi fell sick several days ago.
Although the doctors have been treating her,
the exorcist from the Baohua Hall
said she's haunted by spirits of the dead.
So, we must move the caskets of any concubine
who had a sudden demise, here to the temple.
But it’s inauspicious to undertake this task
in the first lunar month.
Why was it assigned to you?
The exorcist said that
only someone who hasn't been intimate
with His Majesty for a long time
can fulfill such commitment that requires
physical and spiritual purity.
Of course,
I'm not the only concubine who fits the description.
But other concubines considered it bad luck.
So it fell to me.
You have always been cautious
in matters related to death.
Normally, you would never get involved in
rituals for redeeming lost souls.
Meizhuang,
did you really come to the temple
to guide these souls to the Pure Land,
or it was an excuse to visit me?
Given your insightfulness,
I won’t hide it from you anymore.
I asked Wen Shichu
to medicate Princess Wenyi to induce a fever.
And I bribed the exorcist in the Baohua Hall
to suggest the ritual.
All for having a chance to come see you.
You went to such painstaking efforts...
It must be something serious.
Did something happen to Longyue?
No, no, not Longyue.
She is good.
Nothing happened to her.
It is…
It is your father.
He fell gravely ill in Ningguta,
his life is in critical condition.
My father was healthy...
How did he become gravely ill?
Yes...
Even though your father was exiled,
he had been in good health.
I hesitated for days
if I should tell you.
I was afraid that the news would
overwhelm you with sadness.
But…
after turning it over in my mind,
I am more worried for your father's life.
I had to come and tell you.
My father was perfectly healthy.
What exactly happened?
That's my question too.
There is nothing we can do if it was Heaven's will.
But if someone deliberately harmed him ...
That would be truly terrifying.
Do you think...
it's a premeditated act?
I suspect that the Empress did something in secret.
Or ...
it could be Concubine Délice‘s family -
outside of the palace.
I never thought that after all this time,
they would still hound your family relentlessly.
The Zhen family has been exiled to Ningguta.
And I left the palace to practice in a nunnery.
Why are they still persecuting us?
Huan’er,
now is not the time to feel aggrieved.
Your father was plotted against.
Who knows if you will be their next target?
You have to find a way
to bring your father back to Beijing
for medical care as soon as possible.
Perhaps he can recover with proper care.
You are right.
For the time being,
his life is the most important.
As for treating my father,
I will try my best to come up with a way.
Yes.
Your Highness, it's time to go.
We have to return to the palace before dark.
I understand.
Ask the carriage to wait.
Yes, Your Highness, but please don't be long.
Huan'er,
I have to leave now.
Just remember this for me:
preserving yourself
is the most important.
The palace is a dangerous place.
You need to be careful as well.
I don't know when...
we will be able to see each other again.
As long as we are both safe and healthy,
it doesn't matter
whether we get to see each other or not.
Do take care of yourself.
You as well.
How come Mistress skipped dinner again?
Mr. Zhen is not well.
I am very worried, too.
I hope His Lordship can return soon.
He would be able to help us out.
Mistress, what's wrong?
Is it something you ate?
Are you...
Congratulations, Mistress!
It has been less than a month.
Keep your voice down.
You should inform Consort Dowager.
She will be elated to hear the news.
I just learned about my father's illness.
I'm not in the mood for a celebration.
I'll wait untill Yunli is back,
and we can tell Consort Dowager together.
Jade.
The child in my belly ...
is going to call you auntie.
Yurao and our parents
are far away in Ningguta.
I'm afraid that
we can only depend on each other
for the rest of our lives.
My child is also your child.
From now on,
we'll raise him together.
Shall we?
Really?
The child of you and His Lordship,
is also my child.
Jade.
Like the placement of stones at the end of a Go game,
some things are irreversible.
Trying to change such things
will only hurt yourself and others.
But I promise I will give you
everything I can.
I understand.
Some things...
are not fated in life.
They cannot be forced to happen.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember, amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.